Guide to the Barnett Fred Dodge Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Barnett Fred Dodge papers
1930-1972
MS 640
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
104
(110 boxes)
Correspondence, research files, teaching materials, and writings relating to Barnett F. Dodge's (1895-1972) position as chairman of the Department of Chemical Engineering, Yale University, 1931-1963, his participation in professional organizations and his activities as consultant to governments and corporations on technical problems. Among the teaching materials are lectures, problems, examinations, and reports of students. Included also are offprints of papers by Dodge published between 1922 and 1964, speeches, a biography and a small amount of personal papers.
Dodge, Barnett F. (Barnett Fred), 1895-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Barnett F. Dodge, 1972.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, research files, teaching materials, and writings relating to Barnett F. Dodge's (1895-1972) position as chairman of the Department of Chemical Engineering, Yale University, 1931-1963, his participation in professional organizations and his activities as consultant to governments and corporations on technical problems. Among the teaching materials are lectures, problems, examinations, and reports of students. Included also are offprints of papers by Dodge published between 1922 and 1964, speeches, a biography and a small amount of personal papers.
Chemical engineering; Engineering; Chemists; Educators; Engineers; Dodge, Barnett F. (Barnett Fred), 1895-; Connecticut State Water Commission; Armour Institute of Technology; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Chemical Engineering; Yale University. School of Engineering
- Inventory, Circa 1930-1972; 102
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers (Box 1)
  - Program Committee (Box 1)
  - Local Sections (Box 1)
  - General and Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Research Committee (Box 1)
  - Research Policy Committee (Box 1)
  - Future of Institute Committee (Box 1)
  - Equipment Test Procedures (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers (Box 1)
  - President (Box 1)
  - Nuclear Energy Division (Box 1)
  - Nuclear Energy Exposition (Box 1)
  - Committee on Education and Accrediting (Box 1)
  - Publications Committee (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Chemical Engineers (Box 1)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary (Box 1)
  - General Lists (Box 1)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Box 1)
  - Papers by Foreign Engineers (Box 1)
  - Fund Raising (Box 1)
  - "Chemical Engineering Around the World" (Box 1)
  - Analytical Methods (Box 2)
  - Argentina (Box 2)
  - Books by Bliss and Dodge (Box 3)
  - English Versions of Barcelona Lectures (Box 3)
  - Brookhaven National Laboratories (Box 3)
  - LMFR (Box 3)
  - Volatility Processes (Box 3)
  - Chemical Engineering in Australia (Box 3)
  - Chemical Engineering Abroad Japan--Engineering Mission (Box 4)
  - Chemical Engineering Abroad (Box 4)
  - France in General Lille (Box 4)
  - Chemical Engineering Abroad (Box 5)
  - France/Toulouse in Particular (Box 5)
  - Chemical Engineering in France Instituts du Génie (Box 5)
  - Chemical Engineering Abroad (Box 5)
  - South America and Central America Includes Mexico and Puerto Rico Venezuela in Particular Uruguay (Box 5)
  - Chemical Engineering Abroad Spain--Lectures at Barcelona (Box 6)
  - Chemical Engineering 49 Design (Box 6)
  - Lectures on Chemical Engineering at Barcelona, Spain in Spanish (Box 7)
  - Chemical Engineering (Box 7)
  - Education (Box 7)
  - General (Box 7)
  - Europe (Box 7)
  - South America (Box 7)
  - Chemical Engineering 25/First Course in Chemical Engineering (Box 8)
  - Chemical Engineering at Yale (Box 8)
  - Material on New Building and Development of Chemical Engineering at Yale (Box 8)
  - Chemical Engineering (Box 9)
  - 38-44 Bound Sets of Problems and Exams (Box 9)
  - Chemical Engineering 42 Reports (Box 9)
  - Chemical Engineering 42 Reports 1947 (Box 9)
  - Chemical Engineering 192 Material for Lectures and Problems (Box 10)
  - Chemical Engineering (Box 10)
  - 47,191,192,193,194 Bound Sets of Problems and Exams (Box 10)
  - Chemical Engineering 192 Problems and Exams (Box 10)
  - Chemical Engineering 198 Plant Design Reports (Box 11)
  - Compressors (Box 11)
  - General (Box 11)
  - Centrifugal (Box 11)
  - Worthington included in this laboratory (Box 11)
  - Computing and Computers (Box 11)
  - Computers (Box 12)
  - Compressor Auxiliaries (Box 12)
  - Filters, After Coddlers, Flow Meters, Pressure Regulator Unloaders (Box 12)
  - Connecticut Coke 10 Test 1940 (Box 12)
  - Connecticut State Water Commission (Box 13)
  - Metal State Industries Memo No. 1 to No. 12 inclusive (Box 13)
  - Connecticut State Water Commission (Box 13)
  - Metal Industries Memo No. 13 to No. 24 inclusive (Box 13)
  - Connecticut State Water Commission (Box 13)
  - Metal Industries Memo No. 25 to No. 34 inclusive (Box 13)
  - Connecticut State water Commission (Box 14)
  - Metal Industries Memo No. 35 to No. 44 inclusive (Box 14)
  - Control (Box 14)
  - Gauges (Box 14)
  - Humidity (Box 14)
  - Flow (Box 14)
  - Composition (Box 14)
  - Mercoid (Box 14)
  - Correspondence With Former Students (alphabetically) (Box 14)
  - B.F. Dodge, Personal Papers, Talks, Biography, etc. (Box 15–16)
  - B.F. Dodge, Work for NORC on oxygen problems. (Box 17)
  - Reprints of papers by B.F. Dodge., 1922-1953 (Box 17)
  - Reprints of papers by B.F. Dodge., 1954-1963 (Box 18)
  - Memo on Department of Chemical Engineering (Box 18)
  - Reprints of papers by B.F. Dodge., 1964- (Box 18)
  - Energy and Power Generation (Box 19)
  - General (Box 19)
  - Engineering Education (Box 19)
  - Design (Box 19)
  - Reprint of President's Committee (Box 19)
  - Study of Curricula at Other Schools (Box 19)
  - Engineering Educators (Box 20)
  - Design (Box 20)
  - Engineering Education (Box 20)
  - General (Box 20)
  - Study Committee (Box 20)
  - Faculty Opinions (Box 20)
  - Curricula (Box 20)
  - Engineering Societies Center/Special Task Committee (Box 20)
  - Engineering (Box 21)
  - General Teaching Methods (Box 21)
  - Education (Box 21)
  - Foundation (Box 21)
  - Accrediting Societies (Box 21)
  - Engineering (Box 21)
  - Economic Status (Box 21)
  - Manpower (Box 21)
  - Professionalism (Box 21)
  - Licensing (Box 21)
  - John Fritz Medal (Box 21)
  - Engineering Firms (Box 21)
  - UPADI (Box 21)
  - ECPD (Box 21)
  - Phase Equilibrium (Box 22)
  - Gases in Metals (Box 23)
  - Hydrogen Embrittlement/Hydrogen Diffusion in Iron and Steel (Box 23)
  - Hydrogen Embrittlement (Box 24)
  - International Relations/American Institute of Chemical Engineers Committee (Box 24)
  - Low Temperature Engineering/Lectures and Problems (Box 25)
  - Low Temperature Engineering/Drawings of Keyes Oxygen Plant (Box 25)
  - Materials (Box 26)
  - General (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets on properties of plastics. (Box 26)
  - Materials/Heat Transfer Fluids (Box 26)
  - Materials/Steels and Alloys (Box 26)
  - Materials/Steels and Alloys for High Pressure (Box 27)
  - Methanol Synthesis (Box 27)
  - Consulting File from S. Karpen and Brothers. (Box 27)
  - Nuclear Energy/General (Box 28)
  - Oak Ridge/Laboratory Sudies on Desalination (Box 29)
  - Oneida-Waste Treatment (Box 29–30)
  - Instructions for Writing (Box 30)
  - Pressure Technology/General (Box 30)
  - Pressure Technology Catalogs of Material and Equipment (Box 30)
  - Pressure Technology Various Techniques (Box 31)
  - Pressure Technology (Box 31)
  - High Pressure Laboratory/Bridgeman Papers (Box 31)
  - Pressure Technology (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous and General (Box 32)
  - Autoclave (Box 32)
  - Design of Equipment (Box 32)
  - Pressure Technology/"High Pressure Associates" (Box 32)
  - Pressure Technology (Box 32)
  - "High Pressure"/Closures, Seals, Materials (Box 32)
  - Ultra High Pressure (Box 33)
  - Equipment and Technique (Box 33)
  - Problems-Chemical Engineering (Box 33)
  - Problems-Thermodynamics (Box 33)
  - Problems in Graduate Courses at Yale (Box 34)
  - Problems and Miscellaneous Material for Courses in Applications of Thermodynamics (Box 34)
  - Process Design (Box 34)
  - Process Design (Box 35)
  - Process Design Course Material (Box 35)
  - Process Design Problems and Solutions (Box 35)
  - Literature (Box 35)
  - Process Design (Box 36)
  - Problems and Solutions (Box 36)
  - Literature (Box 36)
  - New Developments-reports (Box 36)
  - Processes (Box 37)
  - Professional School Engineering (Box 37)
  - Research (Box 38)
  - Compressibility of Gases/United States Naval Ordnance Laboratory Reports (Box 38)
  - General Russian papers on high pressure. (Box 38)
  - Research (Box 38)
  - Gases in Metals (Box 38)
  - Literature (Box 38)
  - Procurement of Samples (Box 38)
  - Translation of German Papers (Box 38)
  - Research (Box 38)
  - General Office of Naval Research (Box 38)
  - Research (Box 39)
  - General Research Institutes (Box 39)
  - Research (Box 39)
  - Joule-Thomson Effect Drawings of apparatus used at California Institute of Technology. (Box 39)
  - Reviews "Industrial and Engineering Chemistry" (Box 40)
  - Saline Water (Box 40)
  - Annual Reports of the Office of Saline water Proceedings of 1957 and 1962 conferences. (Box 40)
  - Saline Water/Dodge and Esbaya reports (Box 41)
  - Saline Water (Box 41)
  - Dodge and Esbaya reports. (Box 41)
  - General Reports on Saline Water (Box 41)
  - Saline Water/Oak Ridge National Laboratory Reports (Box 41)
  - Saline Water-General (Box 42)
  - Office of Saline Water News Releases/Papers from Wood's Hole conference. (Box 42)
  - Saline Water Conversion/Correspondence with equipment companies and bulletins on equipment (Box 42)
  - Saline Water Conversion (Box 43)
  - Reports, Symposia, Miscellaneous (Box 43)
  - Thermal Insulation (Box 43)
  - Applied Thermodynamics (Box 43)
  - Thermodynamics Book Revision (Box 44)
  - Thermodynamics Book Revision-Industrial chapters (Box 44)
  - Thermodynamics-General/Examinations in graduate courses (Box 45)
  - Thermodynamics Research Laboratory/University of Pennslyvania (Box 45)
  - Thermodynamics (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
  - Jefferis-Norton Oxygen Process Corporation (Box 46)
  - General (Box 46)
  - List of Engineers of Thermodynamics (Box 46)
  - Thermodynamic Properties/General (Box 47)
  - Thermodynamic Properties (Box 47)
  - General (Box 47)
  - Hydrocarbons (Box 47)
  - Thermodynamic properties of Refrigerants (Box 48)
  - Turbo Compressors/Centrifugal and Axial (Box 48)
  - Publications of the Van der waals Laboratory (Box 49)
  - Printed matter and notes: courses, departmental (Box 49–59)
  - Printed matter and notes: courses, departmental (cont'd) (Box 59A)
  - Printed matter and notes: courses, departmental (cont'd) (Box 59B)
  - Desk Files
    - G - V, Miscellaneous (Box 60)
    - A - E (Box 61)
  - Saline Water Conversion (Box 62)
  - Waste Disposal (Box 62)
  - Waste Disposal (Box 63)
  - Water Pollution (Box 63)
  - Water (Box 64)
  - Saline Water Conversion (Box 64)
  - Saline Water Conversion (Box 65–66)
  - Miscellaneous Subject File
    - A - C (Box 66)
    - C - E (Box 67)
    - E - J (Box 68)
    - J - P (Box 69)
    - P - T (Box 70)
    - T (cont.) (Box 71)
  - Course Notes (Box 71–72)
  - Miscellaneous Subject File
    - A - Ap (Box 72)
    - Ap - Ca (Box 73)
    - Ca - Cr (Box 74)
    - D - E (Box 75)
    - E - F (Box 76)
    - F - H (Box 77)
    - H - M (Box 78)
    - M - Pre (Box 79)
    - Pre (cont.) (Box 80)
    - Pre - Pro (Box 81)
    - Pro - Res (Box 82)
    - Res (cont.) (Box 83)
    - Res - S (Box 84)
    - S - U (Box 85)
  - National Defense Research Council
    - A - Ai (Box 85)
    - Ai - G (Box 86)
    - He - Hi (Box 87)
    - Hy - L (Box 88)
    - L - P (Box 89)
    - P - S (Box 90)
    - S - V (Box 91)
  - Consulting
    - A - B (Box 91)
    - B - P (Box 92)
    - P - W (Box 93)
  - General Files
    - A - E (Box 94)
    - E - P (Box 95)
    - R - Y (Box 96)
  - Slides, lantern slides used in classes (Box 97)
  - Lantern slides, negatives, printed illustrations (Box 98)
  - Photographs of mountains (MS list in register file) (Box 98)
  - Report Writing (Literature on) (Box 99)
  - Note cards and printed bibliography cards
    - General - II (Box 99)
    - Oxygen (Box 99)
    - Phase Equilibria (Box 99)
    - Thermodynamics - III (Box 99)
    - Waste Disposal (Box 99)
    - Armed Services Technical Information Agency Publications (Box 100)
    - Catalysis (Box 101)
    - General - I (Box 102)
    - Low Temperature (Box 103)
    - Pressure Technology (Box 104)
    - Thermodynamics - I (Box 105)
    - [Thermodynamics - II] (Box 106)
    - Unit Operations - I (Box 107)
    - Unit Operations - II (Box 108)
  - Yale University. Dept. of Chemical Engineering: departmental papers
    - General correspondence of Dodge as Chairman, 1933-1947 (Box 109)
    - Correspondence re: meetings, speeches, papers, 1930-1938 (Box 109)
    - Correspondence with Armour Institute of Technology, 1940-1941 (Box 109)
    - Account book, 1942-1947, undated (Box 109)
    - Departmental personnel: jobs & applicants, 1940-1946 (Box 109)
    - Dept. of Personnel Study; correspondence papers, 1934-1941 (Box 109)
    - Graduate students: correspondence, applications, 1931-1950 (Box 109)
    - Questionnaires sent to Chemical Engineering alumni, graduates, 1939, 1941 (Box 110)
    - Questionnaires sent to various colleges re: new chemical engineering laboratories, 1940-1941 (Box 110)
  - Connecticut State Water Commission
    - Correspondence, 1936-1941 (Box 110)
    - Accounts, reports, etc., 1926-1953 (Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1945-1954 (Box 110)